Guide to the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) National Office Records WAG.281
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) National Office Records
1930-2023, ongoing
1952-1985
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of Television and Radio Artists
Gautier, Janette
WAG.281
174 Linear Feet in 174 record cartons
12 websites in 12 archived websites.
The American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), founded in 1952, is a union of approximately 70,000 members representing professional actors, journalists, dancers, singers, announcers, hosts, comedians, and disc jockeys from numerous media industries, including television, radio, cable, sound recordings, video productions, commercials, audio books, non-broadcast industrials, interactive games, internet productions, and other digital media. The union traces its origins to the 1937 founding of the American Federation of Radio Artists (AFRA) with 400 members and locals in New York and Los Angeles. In 2012, after numerous attempts, AFTRA and the Screen Actors Guild (SAG) successfully merged to form SAG-AFTRA. This guide describes the records of AFTRA's National office from its founding through 1990. The collection consists of photographs, memoranda, correspondence, meeting minutes, financial records, formal agreements, recorded negotiations, constitutions and by-laws, and legal files documenting claims and arbitrations. The materials document the union's daily operations and governance, in addition to broader labor and social issues through the lens of entertainers and performers, including civil rights, anti-communism investigations, and workers' rights and protections. The collections also includes materials documenting the union's relationships and interactions with related domestic and international guilds and federations for performers.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Separated Materials
AFTRA Magazine and Stand-By! newsletter were separated to the library collection.
Related Archival Materials
Actors' Equity Association Records (WAG 011)
Associated Actors and Artistes of America Records (WAG 110)
American Guild of Musical Artists Records (WAG 209)
American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) New York Local Records (WAG 282)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists National Office, 2008. The accession number associated with this donation is 2008.045.
Donated by the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists National Office, 2008. The accession number associated with this gift is 2008.045.
A small amount of material pertaining to the SAG-AFTRA merger was donated by Jannette Gautier in 2002. There is no acccession number associated with this gift.
http://www.aftra.com/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2012, https://www.sagaftra.org/ was added to the web archive. In 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2019, https://sagaftra.foundation/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2019.139. In August 2020 https://www.youtube.com/user/SAGAFTRA/videos/ and http://youngperformers.sagaftra.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.039. In December 2020 https://members.sagfoundation.org/programs/ was added. The accession number associated with this 2021.060. In June 2021, https://servicesagaftra.custhelp.com/app/sh/home/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.003. In February 2023, https://servicesagaftra.custhelp.com/app/home/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.019. In March 2023, https://sagaftra.libsyn.com/ was added. The accesion number associated with this website is 2023.032. In summer 2023, https://asa.sagaftra.org/ and https://www.sagaftrastrike.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2023.062. In September 2023, https://www.youtube.com/@SAGAFTRA/videos/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.079.
Historical Note
The American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), founded in 1952, is a union of approximately 70,000 members representing professional actors, journalists, dancers, singers, announcers, hosts, comedians, and disc jockeys from numerous media industries, including television, radio, cable, sound recordings, video productions, commercials, audio books, non-broadcast industrials, interactive games, internet productions, and other digital media.
The union traces its origins to several preceding organizations representing members of these disparate groups of performers. Following the 1935 National Labor Relations Act, radio performers in Los Angeles and New York formed the Radio Actors Guild and Radio Equity (an organization under the umbrella of Actors' Equity), respectively. On August 16, 1937, the two organizations combined to form the American Federation of Radio Artists (AFRA) after being granted a charter by the Associated Actors and Artistes of Americas (also known as The Four A's). The union began with locations in Los Angeles and New York; by December of 1937, AFRA had over 2,000 members, including 70% of all radio artists, and had added third location in Chicago, the center for soap opera production. Prominent members of the union's early governance included Eddie Cantor, who served as the first president; inaugural National Executive Secretary Emily Holt; and Broadway actor George Heller, who acted as Ms. Holt's assistant. AFRA members and major radio performers, including Edgar Bergen, Jack Benny, and Bing Crosby successfully negotiated with NBC and CBS on the first collectively bargained agreement in the field, resulting in significant wage increases.
Disputes over television performers led the Associated Actors and Artistes of America to create the Television Authority (TVA), an amalgam of the major existing performing arts unions, on April 16, 1950. In 1951, while jurisdiction was held in abeyance, AFRA negotiated the first Phonograph Recording Code with major recording labels. On September 17, 1952, TVA and AFRA merged to create a new union known as the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), with nearly 10,000 members and Heller as the organization's head. During the 1954 Network Television Code negotiations, the union negotiated the AFTRA Pension and Welfare Plan (later known as the AFTRA Health and Retirement Funds), which stands as the industry's first benefits package and was written into all succeeding agreements. Although early television broadcasts featured live performers, technological advancements in the late 1950s allowed for networks to broadcast repeating programs, leading AFTRA to negotiate the first formula for the payment of replayed performances. These agreements formed the basis of the industry understanding of residuals and syndication. In 1960, AFTRA and the Screen Actors Guild (SAG) held their first joint negotiations on the subject of television commercials.
The mid-20th century entertainment industry blacklist (also referred to as the Hollywood blacklist) that denied entertainment professionals employment because of their political beliefs or associations, real or suspected, created strife and dissent within AFTRA. The New York Local was especially vocal over the issue; their motions were sent to a national vote, but all failed. In 1955, the union passed a national referendum stating that any member who refused to cooperate with any government committee investigating alleged disloyalty or subversive activities "shall be subject to the charge that he is guilty of conduct prejudicial to the welfare of AFTRA" and may be "fined, censured, or expelled from the union by the member's local." In October 1997, AFTRA formally apologized for this position.
In 1974, conservative author and public intellectual William F. Buckley harshly attacked AFTRA's union shop agreements, the basis of union organizing. The U.S. Supreme Court, however, declined to hear the case. A similar but more serious threat came from a lawsuit filed in 1981 by Tuesday Productions, a San Diego based non-union jingle house. They filed anti-trust charges against AFTRA for attempting to organize performers. The settlement drove the union into Chapter 11 bankruptcy in 1982 from which they emerged in 1983 with a verdict that upheld "the unions' right to order members not to work for employers who refuse to enter into collective bargaining agreements."
In succeeding decades, AFTRA signed new agreements in cable, interactive media, and digital performances. Major strikes in 1967 and 1978 occurred when negotiations for various types of contracts broke down. The union, along with SAG, staged a six-month strike against commercial advertisers in 2000. On March 30, 2012, after numerous attempts, the two unions merged, forming SAG-AFTRA.
Source:
http://www.sagaftra.org/history/aftra-history/aftra-history
Scope and Contents
The records of National Office of American Federation of Television and Radio Artists cover the period from its founding as a radio only union in 1937, through the addition of television to its name and jurisdiction in 1952, up to 1990. This collection consists of meeting minutes, constitutions, by-laws, contracts, correspondence, handbooks, newsletters, written agreements, financial statements, programs and records of the union's annual convention, and legal files documenting cases involving members' rights, benefits, and protections. The materials document the union's daily operations and governance, in addition to broader labor and social issues through the lens of entertainers and performers, including civil rights, anti-communism investigations, and workers' rights and protections. The collection also includes materials documenting the union's relationships and interactions with related domestic and international guilds and federations for performers.
Arrangement
The collection consists of ten series:
I: Constitutions, By-Laws, Agreements, Codes and Contracts
II: Administrative Files
III: Conventions
IV: Locals
V: Networks
VI: Negotiations
VII: Merger
VIII: Charges, Claims, and Arbitrations
IX: Other Unions/Guilds/Federations
X: Archived Websites
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Television journalists.; Clippings files.; Blacklisting of entertainers.; Actresses -- United States; Actors -- United States; Motion picture industry -- Political aspects -- United States; Los Angeles (Calif.); Legal documents.; Correspondence.; Communism and motion pictures -- United States.; Manuscripts; New York (N.Y.).; Radio broadcasting -- Employees -- Labor unions; Actors -- Labor unions -- United States; Television broadcasting -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Podcasts; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; Wolff, Sanford I. "Bud"; Heller, George, 1906-; Lewis, Irving; Groot, Kenneth; American Federation of Radio Artists; Screen Actors Guild; Associated Actors and Artistes of America; Television Authority (TVA); American Guild of Musical Artists; Actors' Equity Association; AFL-CIO; American Arbitration Association; Cantor, Eddie, 1892-1964; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists; Gautier, Janette
- Series I: Constitutions, By-Laws, Agreements, Codes and Contracts, 1943 - 1996
  Scope and Content Note
  This series is comprised of constitutions and by-laws for both AFRA and AFTRA, as well as national agreements, codes and contracts. These files document the fundamental principles of the organization and the internal rules for how to conduct activities.
  - Articles of Agreement and Constitution for National Association [AFRA], 1944, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles of Agreement and Constitution, 1953, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles of Agreement and Constitution, 1960, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles of Agreement and Constitution, 1972, 1977, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles of Agreement and Constitution, 1980, 1984, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Changes in Minimum Rates, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Commercial Broadcasting for Radio Artists, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Commercial Broadcasting for Radio Artists, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Commercial Radio Broadcasting, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Commercial Radio Broadcasting, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commercial Radio Broadcasting, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Commercial Radio Broadcasting, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commercial Radio Broadcasting and Transcribed Radio Programs, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Commercial Radio Broadcasting and Transcribed Radio Programs, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Commercial Radio Broadcasting and Transcribed Radio Programs, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - HBO Promotion, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Library Service Transcription for Broadcast Purposes, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minimum Sustaining Agreement for Actors and Singers [AFRA], 1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - NBC-NY Staff Newspersons' Agreement, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - NBC Network Staff Newspersons, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - National Sustaining Radio Agreement, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Network Television Broadcasting (Changes in Minimum Rates), 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Network Television Broadcasting, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Non-Broadcast/Industrial/Educational Recorded Material, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Non-Broadcast/Industrial/Educational Recorded Material: Digest, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Non-Broadcast [/Industrial/Educational] Recorded Material: General, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Phonograph Recordings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Phono Code, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Phonograph Recordings, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Phonograph Recordings, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Phonograph Recordings, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Phonograph Recordings, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Phonograph Recordings, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Radio Recorded Commercials, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Radio Recorded Commercials, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Radio Recorded Commercials, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Radio Recorded Commercials, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Radio Recorded Commercials, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Regulations Governing Agents; Rule 12-A, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Regulations Governing Agents; Rule 12-B, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Slide Film Recordings, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Slide Film Recordings, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Sustaining Radio Agreement, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Television Recorded Commercials, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Television Recorded Commercials, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Television Recorded Commercials, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Television Recorded Commercials, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Television Recorded Commercials [SAG/AFTRA Summary of Agreement], 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Television Recorded Commercials, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Television Recorded Commercials, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Television Recorded Commercials, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Transcribed Commercials (Radio), 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions [and Recordings] for [Radio] Broadcasting Purposes, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions [and Recordings] for [Radio] Broadcasting Purposes, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Transcriptions for Broadcasting Purposes, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Transcriptions for Broadcasting Purposes, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Transcriptions for Broadcasting Purposes, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Transcriptions for Broadcasting Purposes, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Administrative Files
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  This series is comprised of the administrative files of the union, including correspondence of its officers, legal representatives, and Executive Director George Heller. The union's efforts on behalf of its members of color as well as other disenfranchised members are highlighted through the work of the union's many committees, the Department for Professional Employees, and the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. The series also contains materials documenting the union's philanthropic efforts, including the George Heller Foundation and the Theatre Authority, an organization that provides union talent for fund-raising activities and award shows. In order to keep all of the staff involved with the union's daily activities, Read Files (referred to as "Blues" in the National office) consisting of each department's daily correspondence were circulated throughout the office. This series also includes files on the union's pension and health programs, in addition to its interest in and involvement with labor legislation being discusses in Congress.
  - 30th Anniversary Ball, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Accounting Services by Automated Process (ASAP): Termination notice, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Actors' Fund of America: Night of 100 Stars, 1984, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Actors' Fund of America: Stage Relief Fund, Inc., 1948-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Actors' Fund of America: Stage Relief Fund, Inc., Blood Bank, and related material, 1959-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Actors' Work Program: Correspondence and Executive Summary, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ad Audit Inc., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Advertising Council, Inc., 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Advisory Council of National Organizations (ACNO), Apr 1975 - Aug 1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Advisory Council of National Organizations, Sep 1975 - Dec 1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Advisory Council of National Organizations, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Advisory Council of National Organizations, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Agency Department, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Airlines: Airline Pilots Association (ALPA), 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Airlines: Airline Pilots Association International, Case, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Airlines: AFA Comparison, Discipline and Discharge Lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Airlines: ALPA, Bankruptcy, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Airlines: ALPA, Duty of Fair Representation, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Airlines: ALPA, FAA Enforcement of Cases, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Airlines: ALPA, "Equal Access to Justice" Act, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Airlines: ALPA, Profit Sharing Plans, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Airlines: Labor Protective Provisions, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Airlines: Title VII, Mary P. Laffey v. Northwest Airlines, Inc., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Alan Frank and Associates, Inc.: Correspondence and Related Material, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: Farrah Strike General, Clippings, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: Farrah Strike (Report of Sanford Wolff), Sep 1973 - Oct 1973 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: Farrah Strike, Responses to Wolff's Adopt a Farrah Family Request, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - American Association of Advertising Agencies: Correspondence, 1961-1978 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - American Association of Advertising Agencies: Correspondence, 1980-1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - American Civil Liberties Union [ACLU]: Correspondence, Mar 1978 - Apr 1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - AFL-CIO: "AFL-CIO Internal Disputes Plan," Index Digest, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - AFL-CIO: Constitution, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - AFL-CIO: Constitution, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - AFL-CIO: Convention, Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - AFL-CIO: Convention, Report of the Executive Council, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - AFL-CIO: Convention, Reports, Booklets, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - AFL-CIO: Convention, "Resolutions", Book 1, 2, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - AFL-CIO: Convention, Statements Adopted, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, Jan 1973 - Oct 1973 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, Nov 1973 - Dec 1973 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence and Related Materials, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - AFL-CIO: Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - AFL-CIO: Disputes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - AFL-CIO: Disputes, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - AFL-CIO: Disputes, Jan 1979 - Aug 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - AFL-CIO: Disputes, Sep 1979 - Dec 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - AFL-CIO: Disputes, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - AFL-CIO: Fact Finding Committee, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - AFL-CIO: Human Resources Development Institute, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 15)